Guide to the Rafa Nasiri and May Muzaffar Collection AD.MC.092
al Mawrid Arab Art Archive, NYU Abu Dhabi
Rafa Nasiri and May Muzaffar Collection
Ca. 1943-2013
al Mawrid Arab Art Archive, NYU Abu Dhabi
Rafa Nasiri (Iraqi artist, 1940-2013)
May Muzaffar (Iraqi poet and writer, 1940- )
AD.MC.092
3353 Digital Objects
The materials were received in good condition, which enabled the digitization to take place at al Mawrid Arab Center for the Study of Art, NYUAD. Digital surrogates were created for all collection items. Upon digitization, all materials were returned to the owner. Materials were rehoused in archival enclosures as needed.
The collection includes personal papers, correspondence, writing, journals, exhibition materials, photographs, and documentation belonging to Iraqi artist Rafa Nasiri (1940–2013) and Iraqi poet and critic May Muzaffar (1940–), a married couple. They were assembled throughout the couple's life together, and later organized by Muzaffar. Rafa Nasiri was born in Tikrit in 1940. He studied at the Institute of Fine Arts, Baghdad, followed by the Central Academy of Fine Arts, Beijing. A creative and accomplished printmaker, Nasiri received several scholarships to support further study in Europe as well. He played a central role in Iraqi modern art developments, including co-founding the New Vision Group (1969), as well as the advancements of printmaking across the Arab world. Nasiri founded and headed the printing workshop at the Institute of Fine Arts in Baghdad from 1974 until his retirement in 1989. From the mid-1980s until 1991, he maintained a Graphic Studio, "Al Muhtaraf," in Al Mansour neighborhood that presented exhibitions and became a gathering place for events. Nasiri and Muzaffar left Iraq in 1991 for Jordan. Between 1991 and 1997, Nasiri taught painting, printmaking and design at the University of Yarmouk in Irbid, Jordan, then held the position of lecturer at the University of Bahrain and director of the Bahrain Center for the Fine Arts and Tradition. Returning to Amman in 2003, Nasiri battled prostate cancer while maintaining a prolific artistic output, completing notable series like Homage to al-Mutanabi and Homage to Ibn Zaydoun. Rafa Nasiri passed away in Amman in 2013. May Muzaffar was born in Baghdad in 1940. She is a poet, short-story writer, critic, editor, and translator. A prolific and knowledgeable writer on topics of art and culture in Iraq, she helped to shape the Baghdad art scene. A collection of Muzaffar's essays were published in Modern Art in Iraq: Continuity and Differentiation (2015) and she served as an editor for the Bahraini literary journal Thaqafat (co-edited with Nasiri). Other books include Rafa and I: A Story of Water and Fire (2021) [in Arabic], which has now been published in English translation as Story of Water and Fire (Berlin: al Mawrid Arab Center for the Study of Art and Hatje Cantz, 2023). She has written numerous volumes devoted to analysis of the work of Rafa Nasiri, including Rafa Nasiri: 50 Years of Printmaking (2013).
E-records AD_MC_092
Content Description
The Rafa Nasiri (1940–2013) and May Muzaffar (1940– ) Collection contains archival materials including correspondence, postcards, writings, exhibition materials, and photographs assembled over the duration of Nasiri's professional life as an artist and Muzaffar's professional life as a writer. The couple are two of Iraq's most prominent cultural figures of the later 20th and early 21st centuries. Having married on December 31, 1973, Nasiri and Muzaffar lived together in Baghdad until 1991 before moving to Jordan, to Bahrain, and back again to Jordan. The collected materials reflect nearly two decades of formative activities in Iraq as well as subsequent initiatives and projects outside the country. What stands out is Nasiri's prolific production, which is evident in the volume of journals, photographs, and letters as well as exhibition materials (brochures, invites, books, correspondence) from the 1960s until his passing in 2013. Highlights include a unique set of journals, handwritten and illustrated by Rafa Nasiri over a long period, 1976-2003, that detail information about and responses to the personal and professional events as well as practical details of his life. These journals include information on the practical details related to finances, residency permits, commuting costs, feelings of despair, hope, restlessness, as well as notes on students, peers and bureaucrats.
The Collection also contains documents pertaining to the work of poet and art critic Muzaffar, including brochures, invites, press clippings, books, correspondence related to Iraqi art and literary scenes from the 1960s until today. Also represented are numerous photographs documenting artists' gatherings, events, trips and travels from 1963 until 2013. There are several sets of 35mm slides taken by Rafa Nasiri for purposes of documenting or teaching, some of the photographs show trips to heritage sites in Iraq or the artist's several trips to Asilah (Morocco) as well as Germany, Portugal, Spain and China. Most of these trips were taken with Muzaffar, who is present in the images.
Noteworthy aspects of the multifaceted career of Nasiri include his role as a teacher and his founding contributions to many art institutions. Photographs of Rafa Nasiri at the Institute of Fine Arts in Baghdad, where he taught from 1964 to 1989 show the confidence and rootedness he enjoyed as an established figure of the Iraqi art scene. Images from these active years include formative events such as a poster exhibition and the Institute's first graphic art graduates' exhibition in 1977. The collection holds documents from Nasiri's extensive travels, residencies, and collaborations with fellow artists and institutions, showcasing his impact on the regional art landscape. Co-maintained by Nasiri's life-partner Muzaffar, the collection holds details about their shared experiences, friendships, and artistic endeavors.
Conditions Governing Access
Digital surrogates only are held by the repository. Materials not made available online may be consulted in person at al Mawrid, NYUAD. Researchers should contact nyuad.almawrid@nyu.edu to request details or to make an appointment.
Biographical notes
Rafa Nasiri (1940–2013) is considered one of the most influential Iraqi artists of the twentieth century, due to his international experience and experimental interest in material techniques across painting, printmaking, graphic design, and book arts. Nasiri was a central participant in numerous Iraqi and Arab artists' groups and initiatives, among them the New Vision group (est. 1969) and the One Dimension group (est. 1970s). He is celebrated for deriving strategies from East Asian arts for incorporating Arabic calligraphic forms into his paintings and prints in elegantly modern ways. Later in his career, Nasiri undertook a sustained interest in making art books as a medium.
Rafa Nasiri was born in Tikrit in 1940. He graduated from the Institute of Fine Arts, Baghdad, with a diploma in painting in 1959. In his last year of study, he was drawn to a collection of watercolors and Chinese ink prints from an exhibition of Chinese antiques and masterpieces on display in the main hall of the Institute. From 1959 to 1963, Rafa Nasiri moved to Beijing to study printmaking at the Central Academy of Fine Arts. Among his teachers was Huang Yu Yi, who taught Nasiri the traditional ways of applying color, and trained him on accuracy, speed and attention in printmaking. The teacher also shared with the artist the latest art books and magazines that arrived from Hong Kong, and that would allow them both to follow the art trends of the West while being in close contact with the contemporary Chinese art at the time. Throughout the years of his study, and until graduation from Beijing with a Bachelor of Arts, Nasiri exchanged letters and postcards with his family in Baghdad. Much of this correspondence survives in his archive today. In the summer of 1965, Rafa Nasiri went on a two-month road trip with two of his brothers, in which they visited twenty-four Arab and European countries. The artist came into direct contact with Western art at museums and other locations that can be traced in his slide collection of photographs taken during the trip. He also visited Museo del Prado, the Louvre, the British Museum, and Rijksmuseum in Amsterdam, which allowed him to see paintings by Velasquez, Goya, and El Greco, Rubens, Rembrandt, Turner and the expressionists in person. In 1964, Nasiri joined the faculty of the Institute of Fine Arts in Baghdad. A couple of years later, Nasiri received a scholarship from The Gulbenkian Foundation to study at The Gravura, in Lisbon, Portugal, where he received a diploma in printmaking. In his collection are photos taken with his colleagues Hashim Samarchi and Salim Al Dabbagh of their participation in the 1968 graphic art exhibitions at The Gravura.
He returned to Baghdad in the aftermath of the defeat of the Arabs in the 1967 Arab-Israeli War. In response to this major setback, he and colleagues Dia al-Azzawi, Ismail Fattah, Mohammed Muhreddin, Hashim Samarchi, and Saleh al-Jumaie co-founded the New Vision Group in Baghdad in 1969 and issued a manifesto. The collection includes photographs of the group's exhibition at Baghdad's Museum of Modern Art, also known as the Gulbenkian Hall.
A two-year relationship with the emerging poet and art critic May Muzaffar culminated in marriage on the final day of 1973. They started traveling together, and Muzaffar accompanied Nasiri to his artist residencies including to his training at the International Summer Academy in Salzburg in 1974-1975. Nasiri also built a printing press for his own use and moved it to his house in Baghdad, eventually dedicating a space of its own for the press that could also be used by other artists. Rafa Nasiri's Graphic Studio, "Al Muhtaraf," was located in Al Mansour neighborhood from mid 1980s until 1991.
In 1974, Rafa Nasiri founded the Graphic Department at the Institute of Fine Arts, which he directed until his retirement in 1989. In 1991, Nasiri accepted an invitation to teach at Yarmouk University in Irbid, Jordan, located 95 km north of the capital Amman, and the couple left Iraq. Nasiri and Muzaffar lived in Irbid but Nasiri kept a studio in Amman, he also taught printmaking at Darat al Funun in Amman. During this decade, many Iraqi artists including Shakir Hassan Al Said and Ali Taleb were active in the Jordanian scene. Nasiri's views on their activities are included in his memoirs.
In addition to teaching graphic arts and design, Nasiri traveled to participate in exhibitions and events around the world, earning prizes from the International Graphic Biennial, Fredrikstad (1978) and Baghdad Festival of Arts (1986), among others. He also served as jury member in major art events such as the Third World Biennial of Graphic Art, London (1980), Intergrafik, Berlin (1987), International Graphic Triennial, Fredrikstad (1995), and International Graphic Triennial in Cairo (1997). Beginning with the first iteration of the Cultural Moussem of Asilah in Morocco, in 1978, Nasiri and Muzaffar regularly attended and contributed to the building of the printmaking studio in this annual gathering of artists. Materials in the collection document the rich art and literary encounters in Asilah as well as the extended trips the couple made in the region.
Between 1997 and 2003, Nasiri took a new position as lecturer at the University of Bahrain in Manama, where he was also the director of the Bahrain Center for the Fine Arts and Tradition. There he started his series Homage to al-Mutanabi, a series of paintings on canvas and paper, prints, and also artist books produced over several years.
In 2003, Nasiri and Muzaffar returned to Amman and settled in a flat in Jabal Amman with a studio in Jabal al Weibdeh, known as an arts-rich neighborhood. In 2009, Nasiri was diagnosed with prostate cancer, yet he continued to work through his chemotherapy treatment. Among the works he completed in this phase was a collection titled Homage to Ibn Zaydoun. His final exhibitions were two retrospectives in 2013: 50 Years of Painting and Printmaking at the Jordan National Gallery for Fine Arts, Amman, and another at The Financial Harbour Art Gallery, Manama. His authored books include Horizons and Mirrors (2005) and My Journey to China (2012).
Nasiri passed away in Amman in 2013.
May Muzaffar (1940– ) is a poet, short-story writer, critic, editor, and translator. She was born in Baghdad in 1940. Muzaffar studied English Literature at the University of Baghdad and pursued additional studies in Arabic language with prominent religious and literary figures in Baghdad before forging close friendships with key literary figures of the time such as Najib al-Maniʿ, Nizar Qabbani, and Ferial Ghazoul. While starting her career in an insurance company, Muzaffar self-developed skills in oral recitation of poetry and in criticism. She was an active member of Baghdad's art scene. Her poetry books include Nocturnes (1994), Mail from the Orient (2003), and Absence (2014). She translated several books into Arabic that are related to literature and art, including Etel Adnan's novel Paris When It's Naked. A collection of her essays were published in Modern Art in Iraq: Continuity and Differentiation (2015) and she has served as a contributing editor to the Bahraini literary journal Thaqafat. Other books include Anā wa-Rāfiʻ al-Nāṣirī: Sīrat al-Māʼ wa-al-Nār (2021), which was published in English translation as Story of Water and Fire (Berlin: al Mawrid Arab Center for the Study of Art and Hatje Cantz, 2023). She has written numerous volumes devoted to analysis of the work of Rafa Nasiri including Rafa Nasiri: 50 Years of Printmaking (2013). Muzaffar continues to live in Amman, Jordan, and manages Rafa Nasiri Studio in Jabal al Weibdeh, and the annual Rafa Nasiri Graphic Arts Award which honors Rafa's art and life achievements. She maintains the website of Rafa Nasiri and publishes some documentation of his work http://rafanasiri.com.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in the following series: (I) Personal papers; (II) Correspondence; (III) Writings; (IV) Exhibition materials (V) Photographic Prints; (VI) Photographic Slides; (VII) Designs by Rafa Nasiri; (VIII) Other items in the possession of the artist.
Custodial History
The materials were created or collected by two of Iraq's most prominent cultural figures of the late 20th and early 21st centuries, the artist Rafa Nasiri (1940-2013) and the poet and art critic May Muzaffar (b. 1940). The earliest materials date from the 1940s, and continue through their marriage of 40 years between 1974 and 2013.
When Nasiri and Muzaffar left Baghdad in 1991, they did not take their archive, books, or art collections, but instead entrusted a guard to take care of their house and studio. The guard was killed in 2006 during the sectarian violence that followed the fall of Baghdad in 2003. A war-displaced person was employed to maintain the house, but eventually, they had to sell the house and studio in 2013. They sought the help of artist friend Khalid Wahal to move as many documents as possible in batches, shipped in cardboard boxes to Amman with drivers from Baghdad. The majority of the books in their library were given away to acquaintances in Baghdad.
The transported materials, as well as other materials that the couple accumulated in Jordan and Bahrain since 1991, are in the possession of poet and art critic May Muzaffar (b. 1940) as custodian of the estate. Since Nasiri passed away on December 7, 2013, Muzaffar has been organizing, scanning, cataloging and publishing Nasiri's archive including his studies and letters. The collection is kept in her office which was the late artist's studio in Jabal al Weibdeh in Amman, Jordan. The studio also holds Nasiri's paintings and prints, as well as his personal journals, artist books, photographs, and sketchbooks, all of which are inherited and now owned by Muzaffar.
In 2021, al Mawrid's researchers visited May Muzaffar's office and she agreed to loan the collection for digitization, cataloging and publishing as part of the Arab Art Archive. Since January 2022, al Mawrid has been receiving the materials in batches and returning them to Muzaffar after digitization and cataloging.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The materials were borrowed from May Muzaffar in batches for digitization, and then returned.
Related Materials
Some digital materials from the collection are made available on Rafa Nasiri's website, http://rafanasiri.com/, maintained by his studio in Amman under the supervision of May Muzaffar.
Existence and Location of Originals
Original materials are with May Muzaffar in Rafa Nasiri's Studio in Jabal al Weibdeh, Amman, Jordan.
Bibliography
1. Ali, Enass Hussein. "Aesthetics of Light in the Works of the Artist Rafie Al-Nassiry." International Design Journal 8 no. 1 (2018): 255–264. https://idj.journals.ekb.eg/article_86309.html.
2. Al-Hali, Salim Hamid Rashid. "Jamālīyat al-Takwīn al-Fannī fī Rusūm Rāfiʻ al-Nāṣirī" [The Aesthetics of Composition in the Paintings of Rafaʻ al-Nasiri]. Majallat Jāmiʻat Bābil 24 no. 1 (2016): 318–353.
3. Katrib, Ruba. "Representation and Identity: Reflections on Presenting Contemporary Art in an American Museum." Journal of Contemporary Iraq & the Arab World 15 no. 1-2 (2021): 199–214.
4. Khazindar, Mona and Misk Institute, eds. Lulwah Al Homoud and Rafa Nasiri. The Art Library: Discovering Arab Artists series. Milan: Rizzoli, 2022.
5. Mejcher-Atassi, Sonja, ed. Rafa Nasiri: Artist Books. Milan: Skira, 2016.
6. Muzaffar, May. Rāfiʻ al-Nāṣirī: Rassām al-Mashāhid al-Kawnīyah [A Painter of Cosmic Scenes]. Beirut: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2010.
7. —. al-Fann al-Ḥadīth fī al-ʿIrāq: al-Tawāṣul wa-l-Tamāyuz. Beirut: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2015.
8. —. Anā wa-Rāfiʻ al-Nāṣirī: Sīrat al-Māʼ wa-al-Nār [Rafa and I: A Story of Water and Fire]. Beirut: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2021.
9. —. Story of Water and Fire. Trans. Jennifer Peterson. Berlin: al Mawrid Arab Center for the Study of Art and Hatje Cantz, 2023.
10. Muzaffar, May, ed. Rafa Nasiri: 50 Years of Printmaking. Milan: Skira, 2013.
11. Muzaffar, May, and Salah Abbas, eds. Rāfiʻ al-Nāṣirī: al-Nahr wa-Anā ... ʻIshq ʻala Marr al-Sinīn [Rafi Al-Nasiri: the River and I ... A Long Life Passion]. Baghdad: Department of Plastic Art and Department of the Palace of Conferences, 2014.
12. Naef, Silvia. "Not Just 'For Art's Sake': Exhibiting Iraqi Art in the West after 2003." Writing the Modern History of Iraq: Historiographical and Political Challenges. Hackensack, NJ: World Scientific, 2012, 475–500.
13. Nasiri, Rafa. Āfāq wa-Marāyā: Maqālāt fī al-Fann al-Tashkīlī [Horizons and Mirrors: Articles on the Fine Arts]. Beirut: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2005.
14. —. Riḥlatī ilá al-Ṣīn [My Journey to China]. Beirut: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2012.
15. Nasiri, Rafa. "Survival through Art and the Art of Survival." International Journal of Contemporary Iraqi Studies 3 no. 3 (2009): 259–275. doi:10.1386/ijcis.3.3.259/1.
16. Nasiri, Rafa, and May Muzaffar. Khamsūn ʻĀman Bayna al-Sharq wa-al-Gharb: Maqālāt wa-Ḥiwārāt [Fifty Years Between the East and West: Articles and Dialogues]. Beirut: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2019.
17. Nasiri, Sabah, and May Muzaffar, eds. Rāfiʻ al-Nāṣirī: Ḥayatuhu wa-Fannuhu. Beirut: al-Muʼassasah al-ʻArabīyah lil-Dirāsāt wa-al-Nashr, 2010.
18. Rauh, Elizabeth. "Experiments in Eden: Mid-century Artist Voyages into the Mesopotamian Marshlands." Journal of Contemporary Iraq & the Arab World 15 nos. 1-2 (2021): 121–133.
19. Al-Talabany, Ahmad. "Taḥawwulāt al-Takwīn al-Bināʼī fī Āʻmāl Rāfiʻ al-Nāṣirī al-Karafikiyya" [The Development of Structural Composition in Rafa Nasiri's Graphic works]. Majallat Jāmiʻat Bābil 25 no. 7 (31 Dec 2017): 3358–3384. https://search.emarefa.net/detail/BIM-1086966.
Art -- Arab countries; Art, Arab -- 20th century; Baghdad, Iraq; Amman, Jordan; Manama, Bahrain; Art, Iraqi; Painting, Iraqi; Arabic poetry -- Iraq; Iran-Iraq War, 1980-1988; Gulf War, 1991; Art -- Study and teaching; Art criticism--Arab countries.; Graphic arts--Arab countries; Printmaking--Arab countries; Rafa Nasiri (Iraqi artist, 1940-2013); May Muzaffar (Iraqi poet and writer, 1940- ); Institute of Fine Arts (Baghdad, Iraq); Iraqi Cultural Centre (London, England); Yarmouk University (Jordan)
- Series I: Personal Papers
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes Rafa Nasiri's personal papers, identification cards, reports and official work documents and reports related to his teaching years at the Institute of Fine Arts in Baghdad.
  - I.A. Membership and Identity Cards, cuid346
    Membership cards issued by different institutions, including the Iraqi Artists Syndicate issued to Rafa Nasiri in 1985.
  - I.B. Academic Records, cuid347
    Originally consolidated in a thread-bound volume labeled with the name Rafa Kamel Nasiri, these documents comprise a human resources file at the Institute of Fine Arts in Baghdad. Includes evaluations of Rafa Nasiri's teaching performance, invitations, requests to travel, history of vacations, and salary information.
  - I.C. Financial Records and Payslips, cuid348
    Documents related to payments that were issued or received by Rafa Nasriri while he was living in Baghdad.
  - I.D. Other Papers, cuid349
    Groups of personal documents related to Rafa Nasiri.
- Series II: Correspondence
  This series features a large volume of professional correspondence directed to Rafa Nasiri at his Institute of Fine Arts address in Baghdad, as well as postcards and letters, exchanged with artists, writers, and family members, among them letters Nasiri sent to his father and brothers during his years in Beijing.
  - II.A. Correspondence with Family, cuid350
    Includes letters and postcards exchanged between Nasiri and his father, 1960–1979, and with his brothers, including Sofian Nasiri, Talal Nasiri, Munir Nasiri, and Sabah Nasiri, 1961–1963; letters exchanged between May Muzaffar and Rafa Nasiri, 1973 and 1996, including a set exchanged via Fax during their time in Bahrain, and a set exchanged while in Cairo in 1996.
  - II.B. Correspondence with Friends, Colleagues, and Students, cuid351
    Includes letters exchanged with Arab artists, critics, and literary figures including Adonis, Charbel Dagher, Etel Adnan, Farouq Yousef, Fouad Takarli, Ghada al-Samman, Hassouna Mosbahi, Maath Alousi, Nedim Kufi, Nizar Qabbani, Shaker Hassan Al Said, Suad al-Attar, Ferial Ghazoul, Suha Shoman, Ziad Dalloul, and Ismail Fattah. The letters date from the 1970s to 2000s, spanning shifts in geographical location from Baghdad to Amman, Irbid and Manama, back to Amman, and capturing personal and professional news of acquaintances, many of whom were also displaced from Baghdad to Amman then to Europe or to other countries. Letters exchanged from Amman with Nasiri's assistants and former students, many belonging to what is known as the 1980s generation, document their response to the different art academies and art markets of the European cities to which they had to emigrate.
  - II.C. Other Correspondence, cuid494
    Correspondence with institutions or entities not related to art or literature, such as May Muzaffar's first employer, the Iraq Reinsurance Company.
- Series III: Writings
  - III.A. Rafa Nasiri's Journals